王朝
II
美洲狮
Puma.
山的幽灵
Ghost of the mountains.
这只雌狮名叫"鲁普斯特尔"
This female is known as Rupestre.
她住在"巴塔哥尼亚"南部冰原的底部
She lives at the base of the Southern Patagonian Ice Field
在南美洲
in South America.
最近，她声称拥有这条偏远的海岸线
Recently, she laid claim to the isolated shoreline
这是一个大湖
of this great lake.
这是一个养育家庭的理想场所
It's an ideal place to raise a family.
"鲁普斯特尔"正处于一个转折点
Rupestre is at a turning point.
她刚生了一窝四个孩子
She's just given birth to a litter of four.
这是罕见的，当然也是她有史以来最多的一次
That is rare, and certainly the largest that she has ever had.
在这片新领地上建立一个王朝
Establishing a dynasty in this new territory
并将四只幼崽抚养成人
and raising four cubs to adulthood
这将是她一生中最大的挑战
will be the greatest challenge of her life.
美洲狮
解  说
大卫·爱登堡
一个儿子...
One son...
...三个女儿...
...three daughters...
...对这位单身母亲"鲁普斯特尔"来说，一天都不可能懒散
...and no chance of a lazy day for this single mother, Rupestre.
她的幼崽一醒来就玩耍
The moment her cubs awake, they play.
这是学习所需技能
It's the perfect way
最好的方式
to learn the skills needed
以成为致命的捕食者
to become deadly predators.
隐身...
Stealth...
...敏锐的反应...
...sharp reflexes...
...非常灵活
...and great agility.
它们还有很长的路要走
They've got a long way to go.
它们至少还要依赖母亲一年
They'll rely on their mother for at least a year yet.
在一年中的任何时候，养育四只幼崽都是一项挑战
Raising four cubs is a challenge at any time of year,
但随着冬天的临近，她的任务将更加艰巨
but with winter fast approaching, her task will be a formidable one.
每天，"鲁普斯特尔"都会把她的幼崽留在湖边的育儿所里
Each day, Rupestre leaves her cubs in their lakeside nursery
当她去"托雷斯·德尔·佩恩"山脉的
whilst she heads up to the hunting grounds
山麓狩猎场的时候
in the foothills of the Torres del Paine mountains.
"瓜纳科"
A guanaco.
一种野生的美洲驼，几乎是她的三倍大
A wild form of llama, nearly three times her size.
猎杀一只成年的美洲驼是有风险的
Hunting a full-grown guanaco is risky.
一次踢腿就可能是致命的...
A single kick can be fatal...
...但"鲁普斯特尔"别无选择
...but Rupestre has little choice.
美洲狮是隐形高手
Pumas are masters of stealth.
它们绝对是
They have to be.
走近会让一切变得不同
Getting close can make all the difference.
大约每十次狩猎中只有一次成功
Only one in around ten hunts is successful.
虽然今晚她饿肚子了
Although tonight she goes hungry,
"鲁普斯特尔"仍然可以为她的幼崽提供奶水
Rupestre can still provide milk for her cubs.
但除非她自己吃饱
But unless she herself gets a meal,
否则她很快就无法喂饱它们了
she will soon be unable to feed them.
几天后
A few days later,
这家人正在享受一个更好的夜晚狩猎的战利品
the family is enjoying the spoils of a better night's hunting.
她把她的幼崽从湖边的育儿所带出来
She's brought her cubs away from their lakeside nursery
因为它们第一次尝到肉
for one of their first tastes of meat.
她的一个女儿，"科隆"
One of her daughters, Coiron,
已经显示出成为一只特别好奇的年轻美洲狮的迹象
is already showing signs of being a particularly inquisitive young puma.
但在这里的狩猎场
But up here in the hunting grounds,
独自出行却是很危险的
wandering off alone can be dangerous.
这些山麓是30多只美洲狮的家园
These foothills are home to more than 30 rival pumas.
这是"布林卡"
This is Blinka,
只有一只眼睛的成年雌狮
an adult female with only one eye.
她母亲过去统治着湖边地区
Her mother dominated the lakeside territory in the past,
"布林卡"很可能会试图夺回它
and there's every chance Blinka may try to reclaim it
在未来从"鲁普斯特尔"的管控中
from Rupestre in the future.
但现在，却有另外一个问题
But right now, there's a different problem.
"布林卡"在找伴侣
Blinka is calling for a mate.
这个...
This one...
...被称为"奥斯库罗"
...is called Oscuro.
雄性美洲狮是"鲁普斯特尔"家族最大的威胁
Male pumas are the greatest threat to Rupestre's family.
它们经常会杀死不是自己的幼崽
They'll often kill cubs that aren't their own.
幸运的是，"科隆"本能地与她的兄弟姐妹团聚
Luckily, Coiron instinctively rejoins her siblings.
但更重要的是，"奥斯库罗"的注意力牢牢地落在了"布林卡"身上
But more importantly, Oscuro's attention is firmly fixed on Blinka.
在这里，总有被流浪雄狮袭击的风险
Up here, there's always the risk of an attack by a wandering male.
全家人在湖边安全多了
The whole family are much safer at the lakeside.
这里几乎没有猎物，雄性美洲狮很少来这里
There's so little prey down here, male pumas rarely come this way.
这就是为什么这个地方会成为如此宝贵的育儿所
That's what makes this place such a valuable nursery.
但它确实有一个缺点
But it does have one disadvantage.
它不能提供太多的保护，以免受恶劣天气的影响
It doesn't provide much protection from the elements.
冬天来临时，幼崽只有12周大
The cubs are just 12 weeks old when winter arrives.
季节很长，天气只会变得更糟
The season is long and the weather is only going to get worse.
"鲁普斯特尔"需要给它们找个庇护所
Rupestre needs to find them shelter.
山上有洞穴
In the mountains, there are caves,
但对于幼崽们的小脚丫来说，它们还有很长的路要走
but they are a long way away for little legs.
"科隆"泰然自若，就像她的姐妹们一样
Coiron takes it in her stride, as do her sisters,
"丹妮娅"和"丹妮丝卡"很少分开
Dania and Daneska, who are rarely apart.
她们的兄弟，"尼内欧"
Their brother, Neneo,
似乎更喜欢尽可能地靠近他的母亲
seems to prefer staying as close to his mother as possible.
不久之后，这是一个挑战
Before long, a challenge.
这并不是一个大的跳跃，当然也难不住三姐妹
It's hardly a big jump and certainly doesn't deter the three sisters.
但"尼内欧"没有足够的勇气去追随
But Neneo isn't quite bold enough to follow.
重新归队
Back together.
也许下次他会勇敢一点
Perhaps next time he'll be a little braver.
最后，为它们疲惫的双腿提供庇护和休息
Finally, a refuge and a rest for their tired legs.
不像它们习惯的那么舒适...
Not as cosy as they're used to...
...但这是一个舒适的地方
...but an excellent place to hunker down,
防止任何即将到来的风暴
protected from any oncoming storm.
在未来几周
In the weeks ahead,
气温降至零下15摄氏度
temperatures drop to minus 15 degrees Celsius.
冷风肆无忌惮
Icy gales whip up without warning.
"鲁普斯特尔"没必要照顾这么小的幼崽
Rupestre hasn't had to look after cubs as young as this
在以前的冬天里，打猎从来没有比在雪地里更难
in winter before, and hunting is never harder than in the snow.
幼崽们只有在罕见的情况下才会冒险外出
The cubs only venture out on the rare occasion
她已经成功了
that she's been successful.
即使只有四个月大
Even at just four months old,
"尼内欧"比他的姐妹们需要更多的食物
Neneo demands more food than his sisters,
迫使自己处于最佳状态
and forces himself into the best position.
幼崽体重增加越多
The more weight he can gain as a cub,
作为一名成年雄狮，他可能过得越好
the better he's likely to fare as an adult male.
这里的冬天在获取充足食物和避免充分自然力之间
Winter up here is a knife-edge balance between getting enough food
是一个微妙的平衡
and avoiding the full force of the elements.
经过数月的严寒
After months of bitter cold,
最后，太阳横扫了整个领土
finally the sun sweeps back across the territory.
这总是一个重大挑战
It was always going to be a major challenge
对于让四只这么小的幼崽过冬来说...
to get four cubs as young as this through winter...
...但是"鲁普斯特尔"成功了
...but Rupestre has succeeded.
最坏的天气已经过去了
With the worst of the weather behind them,
她可以带家人回到湖边的育儿所了
she can take her family back to their lakeside nursery.
但空气中有入侵者的气味
But there's the scent of an intruder in the air.
这是她必须调查的事情...
This is something she must investigate...
...独自一人
...on her own.
一个陌生者
A stranger.
一只青春期的幼崽，很容易被吓跑
An adolescent cub, easily scared off.
但它并不孤单
But it's not alone.
它的妈妈想把湖边当成自己的家
Its mother wants the lakeside for her own.
"鲁普斯特尔"坚持自己的立场
Rupestre stands her ground.
她只有在必要时才会冒险打架
She'll only risk a fight if she really has to.
入侵者被吓退了
Intimidated, the intruder retreats.
湖边的育儿所再次属于这个家庭
The lakeside nursery belongs to the family once more.
再一次，它成了它们最喜欢放松的地方
And once again, it becomes their favourite place to relax.
整个冬天，当固体食物非常稀少的时候
All through winter, when solid food was so scarce,
"鲁普斯特尔"为她的幼崽提供了奶水
Rupestre has provided milk for her cubs.
这几乎是平常的两倍
That's nearly twice as long as usual.
但现在是时候让幼崽们转向只吃肉的饮食了
But now it's time for the cubs to move on to a meat-only diet.
春天的到来带来了更容易捕捉的猎物
The arrival of spring brings easier prey,
她开始训练她的家人
and she starts training her family.
虽然幼崽们还太小，自己抓不到新生的美洲驼
Although too young to catch a newborn guanaco themselves,
但这是一个机会，看看她是如何做到的
it's an opportunity to see how it's done.
"尼内欧"很快就能照做
Neneo is quick to copy,
但是，到目前为止，他只够自信
but, so far, he's only confident enough
在他母亲身上尝试这种技术
to try the technique on his mother.
离开育儿所
Being away from the nursery
这也让幼崽们有机会探索这片区域
also gives the cubs a chance to explore the territory.
"丹妮娅"和"丹妮丝卡"仍然形影不离
Dania and Daneska are still inseparable.
"科隆"又一次成为了冒险者
Coiron is once again the adventurous one.
在母亲的监护下
Under their mother's watchful eye,
每个人都像美洲狮一样适应着生活
each is settling in well to life as a puma.
随着春天转为夏天，冷空气从冰原中呼啸而下
As spring turns to summer, cold air whips down from the ice field.
今天，风速接近每小时100英里
And today, winds are tearing through the territory at close to 100mph.
更糟的是
To make things worse,
寒冷的大风把家族的气味带到了一只新的雄狮身旁
the freezing gale carries the family's scent to a new male.
这是"卡纳萨"
This is Carnasa.
他想和"鲁普斯特尔"交配，但首先他会试图杀死她的幼崽
He wants to mate with Rupestre, but first he will try to kill her cubs.
"鲁普斯特尔"在她还有一窝崽要养的时候不会和他交配
Rupestre won't mate with him whilst she still has a litter to raise.
她挡住了他的去路，好把他的注意力吸引在她身上
Blocking his path, she keeps his attention on her.
激怒他来战斗
By goading him to fight,
她试图给她的幼崽们足够的时间逃跑
she's trying to give her cubs enough time to escape.
雌性美洲狮会为了保护幼崽而死去
Female pumas will die trying to protect their young.
幼崽几乎看不见了
The cubs are nearly out of sight.
但"卡纳萨"似乎仍决心追赶它们
But Carnasa still seems determined to follow them.
"鲁普斯特尔"很幸运还活着
Rupestre is lucky to be alive.
她现在必须找到分散的家人...
She now has to find her scattered family...
...赶在他之前
...before he does.
她还不知道自己是否给了它们足够的领先优势
She doesn't yet know if she gave them enough of a head start.
随着夜幕降临，她的叫喊无人应答...
As evening draws in, her calls go unanswered...
...迷失在风中
...lost on the wind.
到了早晨，空气还是静止的
By morning, the air is still.
"鲁普斯特尔"找到了她的三只幼崽
Rupestre has found three of her cubs.
但有一个女儿"科隆"失踪了
But one daughter, Coiron, is missing.
也不知道"卡纳萨"
And there's no knowing whether Carnasa
是否仍在这些山上徘徊
is still prowling these hills.
如果她想找到丢失的幼崽
If she is to find her lost cub,
她必须冒着再次丢下其他人的风险
she must risk leaving the others alone again.
她已经十个小时没见到她失踪的女儿了
It's been ten hours since she saw her lost daughter.
她们从未分开这么久
They've never before been apart for as long as this.
她的其他幼崽仍然需要她
Her other cubs still need her.
她不能一直等下去
She can't keep looking forever.
最后...她的呼唤有人应答了
Finally...her calls are answered.
"科隆"躲过了"卡纳萨"
Coiron has eluded Carnasa,
她独自度过了第一个夜晚
and survived her first-ever night alone.
全家人又团聚了
The whole family are back together.
在接下来的几周里
For the next few weeks,
幼崽不会冒险远离湖岸
the cubs don't venture far from the shores of the lake.
"鲁普斯特尔"必须再次分配她的时间
Rupestre must once again split her time
在它们和狩猎场之间
between them and the hunting grounds.
伤痕累累，没什么可炫耀的
Bruised and battered, with nothing to show for it,
每一次失败的尝试都会使她虚弱
each failed attempt leaves her weakened.
回到湖边，情况将变得更糟
Back at the lake, things are about to get even worse.
她的对手"布林卡"生了孩子
Her rival, Blinka, has given birth,
她来认领湖边的育儿所
and she's come to claim the lakeside nursery.
这是她成长的地方，她已经准备好为之奋斗
It's where she grew up, and she's ready to fight for it.
"鲁普斯特尔"措手不及
Rupestre is caught off-guard.
雌狮之间如此激烈的争斗是罕见的
Fights as violent as this between females are rare.
但是为了她自己的幼崽们
But with cubs of her own,
"布林卡"不会让步的
Blinka will not back down.
"鲁普斯特尔"不堪重负，已经输了
Overwhelmed, Rupestre has lost.
湖边对她来说不再安全了
The lakeside is no longer safe for her.
她被迫搬家...再一次
She is forced to move her family...again.
和"布林卡"再打一场是不值得的
It's just not worth risking another fight with Blinka.
它们现在必须抓住机会
They must now take their chances
在狩猎斜坡上的其他美洲狮中冒险
among the other pumas on the hunting slopes.
在10个月大的时候，幼崽们仍然依赖"鲁普斯特尔"提供食物
At ten months old, the cubs are still relying on Rupestre for food.
这么大的一顿饭可以让它们吃上好几天
A meal as big as this would feed them for days.
又失败了
Failed again.
这家人已经快一周没进食了
The family haven't eaten for nearly week.
是时候尝试不同的东西了
Time to try something different.
转而猎杀年幼的"美洲驼"
Switching to hunting young guanaco
意味着以隐形换速度
means trading stealth for speed.
它们应该更容易抓到
They should be easier to catch,
但疲惫和泥泞的地面让她放慢了脚步
but exhaustion and muddy ground slow her down.
奋力一搏
One last push.
成功了，但离幼崽还很远
Success, but far from the cubs.
如果她去找它们，别人可能会偷走她的猎物
If she goes to fetch them, someone else might steal her kill.
她费了半天劲，不敢冒这个险
She's worked too hard to risk that.
首先喂给"尼内欧"
First to the food is Neneo.
如果他有机会挑战像"奥斯库罗"和"卡兰萨"这样的雄狮
If he's ever to challenge males like Oscuro and Carnasa,
他必须学会如何维护自己的统治地位
he must learn how to assert his dominance.
现在，他在姐妹们身上练习
For now, he practises on his sisters.
"尼内欧"的胃口很好，几乎没有什么可以分享的
With Neneo's appetite, there's barely enough to share.
"鲁普斯特尔"必须越来越努力地工作
Rupestre has to work harder and harder.
她找到了年幼的美洲驼
She runs down young guanaco,
有时一天多达三次
sometimes as many as three in one day,
而她的幼崽则信心倍增
while her cubs grow in confidence.
"丹妮娅"和"丹妮丝卡"一起工作，完善了她们的狩猎技能
Working together, Dania and Daneska perfect their hunting skills.
"科隆"自己练习...
Coiron practises on her own...
...甚至取得了一些小小的成功
...with even some small success.
最终，"尼内欧"变得足够勇敢
And eventually, Neneo becomes bold enough
能够亲自与巨兽搏斗
to grapple with giants himself.
只差一点点
So close.
冬天又来了
Winter returns.
这些幼崽现在已经15个月大了
The cubs are now 15 months old.
"尼内欧"已是一个强壮的年轻雄狮...
Neneo is a strong young adult...
...能得到他想要的
...able to get what he wants.
他的姐妹们从她们的母亲那里学到了一些
His sisters have learnt from their mother what it takes
如何让一个雌狮在这里养家糊口的本领
for a female to raise a family here.
现在，为了完成她的幼崽们的独立之旅
Now, to complete her cubs' journey to independence,
"鲁普斯特尔"还有一件事要做...
Rupestre has one thing left to do...
...离开她的家人
...leave her family.
那天...终于来了
And that day...has now come.
她的幼崽们拥有自己生存所需的技能...
Her cubs have the skills they need to survive by themselves...
...即使在这一年中最艰难的时刻
...even at this, the harshest time of the year.
"科隆"是第一个和她的兄弟姐妹分开的狮子
Coiron is the first to separate from her siblings.
她从小就表现出独立的本能
From her earliest days, she has shown an instinct for independence.
"丹妮娅"和"丹妮丝卡"可能会相互扶持好几个月
Dania and Daneska may support each other for many more months,
但总有一天，她们也肯定会分道扬镳
but one day they too will almost certainly drift apart.
雄狮往往最难独立
Independence is often hardest on males.
"尼内欧"将被迫离开他所熟悉的一切
Neneo will be forced to leave everything he knows to battle rivals
与对手争夺新的领地
for a new territory
并找到与之建立自己王朝的雌狮伴侣
and find females with whom to start his own dynasty.
他母亲的训练对他有好处
His mother's training will stand him in good stead.
但故事并没有就此结束
But the story doesn't end there.
安静了几个月后，她带着成年的幼崽出现在高山上
A few quiet months later, with her grown-up cubs high in the hills,
"鲁普斯特尔"又回到了湖边
Rupestre is back down at the lakeside.
尽管困难重重
Against all the odds,
又是个四胞胎
quadruplets yet again.
使人精疲力竭的
Exhausting.
到目前为止，它们有最安全的育儿所...
So far, they've had the very safest of nurseries...
...但是现在有两条血缘线声称拥有这个地方
...but there are now two blood lines that lay claim to this site.
"布林卡"的幼崽可能已经长大并继续前行
Blinka's cubs may have grown up and moved on,
但"布林卡"自己会回来的
but Blinka herself will be back.
未来还会有更多的战斗...
There will be many more battles ahead...
...但是，如果说有哪位母亲有能力和经验
...but if any mother has the strength and experience
确保她的王朝兴旺发达...
to ensure that her dynasty thrives...
...那一定是"鲁普斯特尔"莫属
...it is surely Rupestre.
王朝
外景拍摄
对于历代的工作人员来说
For the Dynasties crew,
讲述"鲁普斯特尔"故事的唯一方法
the only way to tell Rupestre's story
就是去体验"托雷斯·德尔·佩恩"的风景
was to experience the Torres del Paine landscape
就像她一样 -
as she does -
都是步行
all on foot.
到目前为止，我们肯定已经超过1000英里了
So far over the shoot, we're definitely well over 1,000 miles,
约翰·希尔
摄影总监
和猫一起徒步旅行
hiking with the cats.
我真的很喜欢，但我不知道我的膝盖能否撑住
I really enjoy it. I don't know if my knees enjoy it.
美洲狮和工作人员都要与时速100英里的风作战
Both pumas and crew battle 100mph winds
以及不断变化的天气
and constantly changing weather.
当人们问在这里拍摄最难的事情是什么时
When people ask what the hardest thing about filming here is,
老实说，是风
honestly, it's the wind.
有时候走路几乎是不可能的
It's almost impossible to even walk sometimes.
很难看到任何东西
It's very difficult to see anything.
尼科·拉各斯
生物学家/追踪者
是的，这是我最喜欢的办公室
Yeah, this is my favourite office.
自从我开始在公园工作
Since I started working here in the park,
我认识很多美洲狮，我最喜欢的是"鲁珀斯特"
I know many pumas, and my favourite's Rupestre.
"尼科"已经和美洲狮们合作十年了
Nico has been working with pumas for ten years,
帮助工作人员们树立正确的心态
and helps the crew get in the right mind-set.
你需要耐心
You need to be patient.
你需要非常专注
You need to be very concentrated
和动物一起工作时
to work with the animals,
想想美洲狮为什么要走这条路
to think why the pumas are taking this route,
或者另一条路线
or a different route.
这是一件美好的事情
It's a beautiful thing to do.
不久，工作人员们就进入了"鲁普斯特尔"的世界
Before long, the crew settle into Rupestre's world
反过来，对她来说，他们也成了风景的一部分
and, in turn, for her, they become part of the scenery.
她完全无视他们的存在
She totally ignores their presence.
然而，幼崽们有点好奇
The cubs, however, are a little more inquisitive.
我们在跟踪这些幼崽
We're following these cubs.
你知道，我们真的在看着它们长大
You know, we're literally watching them grow up.
这真是一次很棒的经历
It's a really cool experience
和同一个家庭待上几个月
to spend months with the same family,
并且，你知道，真正了解它们
and to, you know, really get to know them.
住在离家人如此近的地方意味着
Living so close to the family means
工作人员还见证了最艰难的时刻之一
the crew also witness one of the toughest moments
在猫的生活之中...
in the cats' lives...
...当"卡纳萨"袭击时
...when Carnasa attacks.
我们看不见她和幼崽了
We lost sight of her and the cubs,
所以我们非常担心，因为我们不知道情况
so we were very worried because we didn't know
如果幼崽受伤或死亡的话
if the cubs had been injured or died.
现在天太黑了，所以我们知道明天会发生什么
Now it's too dark, so we'll know what will happen tomorrow.
昨晚我们失去了"鲁普斯特尔"的消息
We lost Rupestre at the end of last night.
玛丽·梅尔维尔
助理制片人
是的，我们现在正试图找到她和幼崽们
Yeah, we're now trying to find her and the cubs.
她在这方面做得很好
She's done so well getting this far.
我们会继续找的
We're going to keep looking.
经过一个不眠之夜
After a sleepless night
走了很多路，她没事我就放心了
and lots of walking, I'm just relieved that she's OK.
这真是令人印象深刻的观察
It was really impressive watching
"鲁普斯特尔"拖了他足够长的时间，使幼崽们都能散开
Rupestre hold him off long enough that the cubs could all scatter.
我想我们真的很欣赏她的临危不惧精神
I think we really appreciate the struggle that she faces and
...和在这里做一只美洲狮所需要付出的艰苦努力
...and just the hard work that goes in to being a puma here.
随着幼崽成年
As the cubs reach adulthood,
它们最大的威胁可能不再来自其他美洲狮
their biggest threat may no longer be from other pumas
而是来自外面的人类世界
but from the human world outside.
"鲁普斯特尔"的幼崽们可能会跋涉数英里去寻找领地
Rupestre's cubs might travel for miles looking for a territory,
越过保护区
heading beyond protected areas
并进入家畜牧场，称为"埃斯坦西亚斯"
and onto livestock ranches, known as estancias.
"尼科"亲眼目睹了美洲狮面临的问题
Nico has witnessed first-hand the problems that pumas
当它们和人类世界发生碰撞时
and people face when their worlds collide.
羊是诱人的猎物
Sheep are tempting prey.
一些牧场可能会损失10、15或20英镑
Some estancias can lose up to 10, 15 or 20,
甚至有20%的牲畜在一年内被捕食
even 20% of their livestock in a year because of predation.
他们处理这个问题的方式是
The way they deal with this problem,
如果他们看到美洲狮，就会猎杀它
if they see a puma, they hunted it and they killed it.
在最大的牧场上
On the biggest ranches,
一年内可能会杀死50多只美洲狮
over 50 pumas could be killed in a single year.
"尼科"在附近的一个农场工作
Nico is working with a nearby ranch,
"塞罗·吉多"，是一种解决方案
Cerro Guido, on a solution.
经过特殊训练的守护犬
Specially trained guardian dogs.
它们整日整夜和羊住在一起
They live all day and night with the sheep.
它们开始吠叫，美洲狮也只好离开了
They go and start to bark, and the pumas, they go away.
美洲狮是伏击猎人
Pumas are ambush hunters,
而狂吠的狗消除了这种惊险的因素
and the barking dogs take away the element of surprise.
我们已经用狗好几年了
We have been using the dogs for a couple of years,
结果可能是惊人的
and the results can be astonishing.
这些狗显著减少了狮子对绵羊的捕食
The dogs significantly reduce predation on the sheep
美洲狮又开始捕猎野生猎物
and the pumas return to hunting wild prey.
当美洲狮不杀羊的时候
When pumas don't kill the sheep,
牧场主不会杀死美洲狮
ranchers don't kill the pumas.
为了保护牧场里的美洲狮
Protecting the pumas inside the ranch,
我们正在维护一个与"托雷斯·德尔·佩恩"类似的区域
we are protecting a similar area than Torres del Paine,
所以我们要加倍爱护
so we're doubling the protection.
"鲁普斯特尔"的儿子正好赶上了这次成功运作
This success is just in time for Rupestre's son.
上次摄制组拍摄他的时候，他正朝着这个牧场走去
The last time the crew filmed him, he was heading towards this ranch.
"尼科"的工作可能有助于给他一个更安全的未来
Nico's work could help to give him a safer future.
也许"鲁普斯特尔"的儿子会找到一个安全的地方繁殖
Probably the son of Rupestre will find a safe place to breed,
留下来，让这里成为他的家
to stay, to make this place his home.
希望有一天，更多的牧场能用守护犬
The hope is that, one day, many more ranches will replace guns
取代枪支
with guardian dogs.
我们为美洲狮和人类在做中间工作
We were working in the middle for both pumas and people.
我们想把它传播到"巴塔哥尼亚"
We want this to be spread out, all over Patagonia.
美洲狮和人类世界将继续重叠
Puma and human worlds will continue to overlap,
但像这样的新解决方案才可能会让"巴塔哥尼亚"
but new solutions like this may allow Patagonia's
最有魅力的捕食者
most-charismatic predator to thrive
在整个非洲大陆茁壮成长
across the whole of the continent.
下一次，在肯尼亚尘土飞扬的平原上...
Next time, on the dusty plains of Kenya...
...一个没有经验的领导者
...can an inexperienced leader
让她的家人团聚...
bring her family back together...
...给她刚出生的小象
...to give her newborn calf
生存的机会
a chance of survival,
延续她的古老王朝？
and carry on her ancient dynasty?
制作及导演
费利西蒂·兰切斯特
摄影导演
约翰·希尔